Continue. Sad that we missed some of that good material on the
audio but okay. Anyway, so that's the מחלוקת רש"י ורבנו תם. Machloket
Rashi ve-Rabbeinu Tam. I should say there's one final issue, which is
very interesting. You remember we talked about the הלכה Halacha of כסדרן,
Kesidran, that the פרשיות Parshiot have to be written in order, and
if they're written out of order, then you can't use them. They
have to be written sequentially. What defines sequential for רבנו תם? Rabbeinu
Tam? Is it the way in which they're placed or the way
they appear in the תורה? Torah? So תוספות Tosfot cannot imagine
that there should be one order for the way you write them
and the other order for the way you place them. Nevertheless, and
but he quotes some גמרות Gmarot or whatever, within this debate, and
nevertheless, actually that is how we פוסקין. Pasken.
So, this is from this book I would show you before, this
illustrated guidebook here, you're gonna hand this out. Anyway, they got a
nice little picture here at the very end. The very last few
pictures is, here's a guy, here it has the orders for רש"י
Rashi and רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam תפילין, Tefillin, and it basically showed
you how you have to write תפילין Tefillin according to רבנו תם.
Rabbeinu Tam. If you're writing for the של ראש, Shel Rosh, it's
not a big deal because you just write the פרשיות Parshiot in
order in which they're written, and then you place them in a
different order in their compartments. But how about when you're writing in
the של יד? Shel Yad? It's all on one קלף. Klaf. So
if you look at this picture near the end, you basically have
to write like this: leave a blank space, write the fourth thing,
and then go back and go in the space. Because the basic
point is that he says that the order דהויה באמצע, de-havaya be-emtza,
but the order of writing is the way it's written in the
תורה. Torah. So the way it's written in the תורה Torah is
one, you write the order of the פרשיות Parshiot appear. If we
were to number them the way they appear in the תורה, Torah,
it's קדש, Kadesh, והיה כי יביאך VeHaya Ki Yeviacha is one, two,
שמע Shma is three, and והיה אם שמע VeHaya Im Shamoa is
four. One, two, three, four. The way they're put in the תפילין
Tefillin is one, two, four, three. So what רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam
says is, okay, you put them in one, two, four, three, but
you have to write them one, two, three, four. Not a big
challenge in the של ראש. Shel Rosh. It is a bigger challenge
in the של יד. Shel Yad. So you see the way you're
writing for רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam is one, two, three, four. You
have to leave a blank space and go back and fill it
in because the הלכה Halacha of כסדרן Kesidran requires the order in
which they appear in the תורה, Torah, not the order in which
they are put in the תפילין. Tefillin. Very bizarre. תוספות Tosfot does
not like that idea, but that's actually the way we פוסקין Pasken
within the position of רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. Okay, so those are
some of the issues with רש"י Rashi and רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam.
Yes?
I mean, maybe this is קורא כסדרן korei kesidran that you were,
maybe it's referring to the של יד. Shel Yad.
Right.
Because the של ראש Shel Rosh is four separate
ones.
Right.
Although you could, we saw the other day, you could do them
on one thing if you kind of curl it up. But maybe
קורא כסדרן korei kesidran means if you were to take it out
and read it. And unroll it. Right.
Right. For רש"י Rashi that works better, right. Yeah, right. I don't
know. It is a funny phrase, הקורא. ha-korei. Okay, anyway, that's the
debate of רש"י Rashi and רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. We've seen why
רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam emphasizes I think and expressed in this very
somewhat humorous or very שאלות ותשובות מן
השמים She'eilot u-Teshuvot Min HaShamayim where it has it as a debate
of God and the angels, but that the logic of רבנו תם
Rabbeinu Tam seems to be expressed in this idea of שמע Shma
והיה אם שמע VeHaya Im Shamoa that the שמע Shma is at
the outside. Don't bury שמע, Shma, what they call that in the
newspaper business, don't bury your lead. You don't want to bury שמע
Shma in the middle. That seems to be the logic of רבנו
תם. Rabbeinu Tam. But anyway we פוסקין Pasken like רש"י Rashi that
you do it in the order in which it's written. Okay, let's
now continue from the last two lines of ל"ד עמוד ב'. Lamed
Dalet Amud Bet. Is this the only place it says לא בשמים
היא? Lo Bashamayim Hi? Is this the only place? No, it says
לא בשמים היא Lo Bashamayim Hi and the famous גמרא Gemara in
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia which is exactly about God not having a
voice in הלכה Halacha discussion, about them debating about whether something was
טמא tamei or טהור tahor and the walls of the בית מדרש
Beit Midrash bending in and the heavenly voice coming out, which is
what makes this whole שאלות ותשובות מן השמים She'eilot u-Teshuvot Min HaShamayim
so funny because the whole point is it's not מן השמים, min
hashamayim, it's לא בשמים היא. lo bashamayim hi. But I guess he
figured, well if we can't figure it out, if you're going like
רש"י Rashi it's פסול pasul for רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, רבנו תם
Rabbeinu Tam פסול pasul for רש"י, Rashi, every now and then you
do have to turn to God. But anyway, that's what makes it
so humorous is that it's so non-halachic, that process. Okay, אמר יוחנן
אמר רב. Amar Yochanan amar Rav. Last two lines.
Giving no logic or reason, reaching a nice compromise between the two.
Well it's not a compromise but right. אמר יוחנן אמר רב: Amar
Yochanan amar Rav: החליף פרשיותיה פסולה. Hichlif parshioteiha pesulah. If you reverse
the order, the order is not just a preference, the order is
מעכב me'akev and this is why you can't be יוצא yotzei both
רש"י Rashi and רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. If you somehow switched the
order, it's invalid.
אמר אביי לא אמרן אלא גוייתא לברייתא וברייתא לגוייתא. Amar Abaye: Lo
amaran ela gevayata l'vrayta u'vrayta l'gevayata. And here again it shows that
it's not just about sequence, it's about a concept of inner and
outer. The idea of reversing is a problem if an inner one,
an inner compartment, compartment two or three, you placed in box one
or four. Or an outer one you placed in an inner one.
You switched something's inner or outer designation. גוייתא לגוייתא וברייתא לברייתא, Gvayata
l'gevayata u'vrayta l'vrayta, but an inner to an inner, reversing two and
three, which is what happened with the תפילין Tefillin of the Qumran,
it was רש"י Rashi with two and three reversed, or ברייתא לברייתא,
vrayta l'vrayta, reversing. reversing one and four, לית לן בה, leit lan
bah, that's not a concern.
אמר ליה Amar lei רבא Rava יתיב בראייתא, yativ braisa, not so
much sequence as about inner and outer, which again sort of shows
רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam's mindset. We don't want שמע Shema just in
the right sequence, we want it on the outside. Outside is sort
of like important. Okay, אמר ליה Amar lei
רב פפא Rav Papa לאביי l'Abaye because it's important.
Right, right. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava said back to
אביי, Abaye, מאי שנא mai shna דייתיב לבראייתא בראייתא דייתיב, d'yativ l'braisa
braisa d'yativ, why can't you do inner to outer? דלא, d'lo, it's
not good. דהך דבעי למיחזי אוירא d'hach d'ba'ei l'mechzi avira לא קחזי,
lo kachzi, the one that has to be exposed to the outside,
to the air, is not exposed, והאי דלא קבעי למיחזי אוירא v'hai
d'lo kaba'ei l'mechzi avira קחזיא, kachzia,
and the one that's not supposed to be exposed to the air
is being exposed. So you know, that thing's in the wrong place.
Inner and outer is a fundamentally different type of a compartment. That's
why you don't like it. So he says, so you know what,
if that's true, בראייתא לבראייתא גביזתא לגביזתא, braisa l'braisa gavizta l'gavizta, outer
and outer, reversing one and four, or inner and inner, two and
three, נמי nami is also a problem. Why? הך דבעי למיחזי אוירא
דימין hach d'ba'ei l'mechzi avira d'yamin קחזי אוירא דשמאל, kachzi avira d'smol,
the one that's supposed to be exposed to the right-hand air, the
air from the right-hand side of the box, is now being exposed
to the left-hand air, ודשמאל קחזי אוירא דימין, v'd'smol kachzi avira d'yamin,
and the left to the right. Meaning, it's not just-you can't just
genericize it and say outer and inner. If things have a place,
then every place is significant. Left-hand outer, right-hand outer, leftmost inner, rightermost
inner, and any change is a change and is not the right
place. אלא, Ela, he says, לא שנא, lo shna, it doesn't matter,
and either way is invalid. But I think what is interesting about
this, in addition because יגאל ידין Yigael Yadin quotes this גמרא Gemara
in explaining the תפילין Tefillin that he found, which was רש"י Rashi
with the inner ones reversed. But besides that, I think what's interesting
is is that it reflects the idea that presumably there was a
certain amount of variation going on. I mean, אביי Abaye is not
merely just saying it theoretically, but maybe also saying it because there
was a certain amount of variation going on, which also explains how
רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam and רש"י Rashi could be referring to two
different traditions about the תפילין. Tefillin. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara goes
on and says the following: דאמר רב חננאל אמר רב, d'amar Rav
Chananel amar Rav, תיתורא דתפילין הלכה למשה מסיני. Titura d'Tefillin Halacha l'Moshe
mi'Sinai.
What is the תיתורא? Titura? I meant to bring my own תפילין,
Tefillin, but we'll deal with the examples here. So if you take
a look at this nice picture that I handed out, sorry again
for people that are online. Okay, here is-here's the outer view of
the תפילין, Tefillin, the של יד shel yad and the של ראש.
shel rosh. Okay,
so this little thing here which has the notch in it and
that is notched in at the bottom, that's called the מעברתא, Ma'abarta,
which is like the bridge. That's the thing you pass the strap
through. The thing that is the base, which is also square, right,
is called the תיתורא. Titura. This is the בית, bayis, the cube.
Then you have the square base that it sits on, okay? And
then you have the extension of that over here with the notch
where you pass-which is the where you pass the strap through. So
the base is called the תיתורא Titura and the extension here is
called the מעברתא. Ma'abarta. They actually specifically say that you have to
notch the מעברתא Ma'abarta in order to sort of distinguish it to
allow the square aspect of the תיתורא Titura to be ניכר. nikar.
If you didn't notch it, it would be a rectangular. You couldn't
just in your mind draw a line. You actually have to create
a physical difference between the מעברתא Ma'abarta and the תיתורא Titura so
the תיתורא Titura can remain square. There's a debate of רש"י Rashi
and תוספות Tosafot whether this תיתורא Titura has to be one piece
of leather with the בית, bayis, with the box, because you could
make this בית bayis of the four compartments, obviously we said before
you don't like four separate compartments and glue them together, you like
four protrusions in a leather. But then do you glue that or
sew that on top of a base, or was that all part
of the base? So רש"י Rashi says it's all part of the
base, תוספות Tosafot says that's not our מנהג. minhag. Our מנהג minhag
is to even make it separate from the base and to... but
our מנהג minhag is no, we make it all one, you know,
עור אחד. or echad. But in different times they didn't always have
that luxury and they didn't have the technology.
And is the מעברתא Ma'abarta part of the תיתורא Titura but you
just separate it afterwards or you actually take two separate pieces of
leather then you sew it together?
No, I think that the way we make it is that we
make it all עור אחד or echad even including the מעברתא. Ma'abarta.
So but then you separate it out, you know,
the way you cut it. The way you cut it, exactly. Okay,
so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
תיתורא דתפילין, Titura d'Tefillin, having a base, or maybe the squareness of
the base, although we'll get to the squareness in a minute, הלכה
למשה מסיני. Halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai. So now we start introducing הלכה למשה
מסיני, Halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai, which is quite interesting. You know, the whole
discussion before about the order, we didn't say it. But also, you
know, the גמרא Gemara started off using סברא. sevara. Does it matter
if you reverse inner and outer and dot dot dot? So you
do get a sense that some of that although these פרשיות parshiyot
and we say the order is מעכב me'akev at a certain level,
a lot of things are דאורייתא d'Oraisa מעכב me'akev that aren't הלכה
למשה מסיני Halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai that חז"ל Chazal learned out from their
סברא. sevara. But I think it especially strikes us as a little
funnier when we are learning about תפילין. Tefillin. On the one hand,
for people that are have learned it before, you know that הלכה
למשה מסיני Halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai is said all the time by תפילין.
Tefillin. How do we know this? הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai.
How do we know that? הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai. Because
there's not so many פסוקים pesukim that tell us. But also because
we are talking about a very sort of concrete physical object that
the תורה Torah is describing, you know, there's a sense like we're
not just using our סברא sevara to figure it out, the תורה
Torah probably was referring to... Something specifically. Like if I told you,
oh yeah, you know, the ארבעה מינים שבלולב, Arbaah Minim shebaLulav, פרי
עץ הדר, Peri Etz Hadar, what's פרי עץ הדר? Peri Etz Hadar?
Well, maybe there was a time that they thought that meant, you
know, an apple or a lemon, but in the end חזל Chazal
said it meant an אתרוג Etrog and we פסקנו paskened that way
and that's the nature of תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-ba-al Peh. You
probably feel a little funny about that because not that you don't
accept the תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-ba-al Peh, you know חזל Chazal
are empowered to interpret things and like, you know, that was the
whole story about משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, but because you think the
תורה Torah is describing a specific physical object there probably was a
tradition what that physical object meant, as opposed to if the תורה
Torah says don't do מלאכה Melacha on שבת Shabbos where maybe the
definition of מלאכה, Melacha, you know, might have gone through a תורה
שבעל פה Torah she-ba-al Peh process of interpretation. And רמבם Rambam says
that explicitly by the
מינים שבלולב, Minim shebaLulav, although רמבם Rambam tries very much to minimize
the context of תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba-al Peh where it only
is a very small number of places, most of the time הלכה
למשה מסיני, Halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai, most of the time תורה Torah is,
you know, humanly derived, but he says and the גמרא Gemara quotes
פסוקים Pesukim by the ארבעה מינים שבלולב, Arbaah Minim shebaLulav, רמבם Rambam
says we have to assume that that was always a מסורה. Mesorah.
And even the פסוקים Pesukim to try to prove what it means
was only after the fact, there was always a מסורה Mesorah what
those ארבעה מינים Arbaah Minim meant. I think there's an intuition that
with these sort of like concrete objects there was probably something very
specific that the תורה Torah was referring to. Anyway it is interesting
within all that to note that we have not really said הלכה
למשה מסיני Halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai until this point. And now we start
saying that a lot of the details are הלכה למשה מסיני, Halakha
le-Moshe mi-Sinai, but some of the things that are maybe we know
from the פסוקים Pesukim are there, we just don't know the specifics
of them. We know there are ארבע פרשיות, Arba Parshiyos, it says
four times, we had a whole דרשה Drasha טטפת, Totafos, טט, Tat,
פת, Pat, and that equals four compartments. Those types of things we're
not saying הלכה למשה מסיני. Halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. They are ultimately anchored
in פסוקים Pesukim although we use some סברא Svara to figure out
what it means. But this list of things there's no פסוק Pasuk
to even base ourselves on and this is הלכה למשה מסיני. Halakha
le-Moshe mi-Sinai.
It just seems a little bit arbitrary because, you know, as you
say the פת Pat and the כט, Kat, you say that means
four פרשה, Parsho, but to get four compartments out of that, I
don't see it.
Well, no, you could also know four פרשיות Parshiyos from the תורה
Torah says four times put on תפילין, Tefillin, you know, but we
don't have טט Tat and פת Pat by the של יד, Shel
Yad, we only have it by the של ראש. Shel Rosh. So
if anything it, but yeah, I understand as all things that are
תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-ba-al Peh, you know, when you use סברא
Svara you could say other things as well. Yeah.
Wouldn't it make it have their own tradition if a father handed
down the art of making a...
That's also true. Right, there probably is, that's also true as well,
there probably is a very strong traditional school about that. So let's
take a look at the list of things, let's just read this.
The list of things that are הלכה למשה מסיני. Halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai.
צורת תפילין Tzurah de-Tefillin הלכה למשה מסיני, Halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai, the base.
אמר אביי Amar Abaye מעברתא דתפילין Mabarta de-Tefillin הלכה למשה מסיני, Halakha
le-Moshe mi-Sinai,
that's the bridge that I mentioned, the part where the strap goes
through that extends beyond the base. ואמר אביי V'amar Abaye שין של
תפילין Shin shel Tefillin הלכה למשה מסיני, Halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai,
the outer שין Shin that we put on the של ראש, Shel
Rosh, right, and we have it on both sides although the גמרא
Gemara isn't explicit about that. That's הלכה למשה מסיני. Halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai.
But you have to have one. But you have to have one.
What about the four-legged? We'll talk about that in a minute. וצריך
שיגיע חריץ למקום התפר V'tzarikh sheyagiya kharitz limkom hatefer and the the
notch, what? I have it here, let me see. Do you want
to?
The knot has
to reach the place of sewing. What does it mean the knot
has to reach the place of sewing? There are two interpretations. One
is that it means the point of the שין, Shin, which right
here, the point of the שין Shin has to touch the actual
base because there are if you take a look at some of
the pictures here I showed later, okay, here's a nice picture of
the point of the שין. Shin. Anyway, but this you see the
point of the שין, Shin, but also this whole thing, the בית,
Bayis, it there's a part that it's sort of sewn, although it's
one עור, Or, there's sewing and stitches that keep it combined to
the base. And that's called מקום התפר Makom ha-Tefer of the sewing.
Okay let me show you here. For example you see you have
to open it up, right, in order to put in the parchment,
so there's got to be holes that you do to sew it
closed afterward. So that's a certain amount of sewing. And here, where
you have the, so here, so those are the and then there's
also a place I thought I showed you before where it showed
you the, where it showed you the line oh here.
Okay, so you also do a whole series of threading. It's not
really that functional,
but, but it's done because the גמרא Gemara basically said that you
need to get a string between the, between the compartments. So you
do a whole series of threading here between the compartments. Can you
see that? So you do a threading to close the box, to
close the קציצין, Ketzitzin, and you do a threading between the compartments.
So anyway what we're saying now is that the שין, Shin, the,
so it had to, at least one way of reading that is
the point of the שין Shin has to reach the place of
sewing. So here the place of sewing where this contacts with the
base where you'd do some sewing either between the compartments or to
seal them. That has to go to the bottom. The point of
the שין Shin has to reach the bottom. That's one way of
understanding חריץ. Kharitz. The other way of understanding חריץ Kharitz probably more
literally is the lines here that go between each of the compartments.
This is a חריץ. Kharitz. It's a furrow, right, that goes... good
between each of the compartments. So that that's probably the better reading
here of the אביי Abaye statement, that that furrow has to go
all the way to the bottom. The compartments also have to be
a little bit divided at the top. They have to really be
separate compartments, again from one piece of leather, but fully separate compartments
reaching all the way down to the actual base. Okay, so let's
take a look, let's continue reading that.
Okay, רב דימי מנהרדעא Rav Dimi mi-Narda אמר, amar, רב דימי מנהרדעא
Rav Dimi mi-Narda says, כיון דמינכר לא צריך. keivan de-minchar lo tzarich.
No, as it's obvious they're separate compartments, it's not needed, which means
even if the compartments are just a little bit separated at the
top, the furrow does not have to reach all the way to
the bottom. You understand that the way we look at it now
we don't even see the furrow, or so slightly, but ultimately it's
constructed by a furrow and then the pieces are pushed together. So
does that furrow, right, if this is made like a glove essentially,
does the furrows have to get to the base or can it
basically be, you know, more just little separations at the top? So
he's saying it's enough that it's little separations at the top, that
shows they're different, it doesn't have to get all the way to
the base.
Okay, ואמר אביי, ve-amar Abaye, and אביי Abaye says, האי קלפא דתפילין
צריך למיבדקיה דדילמא אית ביה ריעותא. hai klapha de-tefillin tzarich le-mivdakei de-dilma
is bei re'usa. So now we're leaving the בתים battim and back
to the קלף. klaf. You have to check your קלף klaf before
you write on it that there shouldn't be a tiny little hole
and then if you're writing your letter, then the hole appears right
alongside the letter and it's not מוקף גויל. mukaf gvil. And as
we know, it's a real disaster if your תפילין tefillin have a
problem because then it has to be כסדרן. kasidran. So if you
had one problem in one of the פרשיות, parshiyos, you basically have
to do all four פרשיות parshiyos again because every פרשה parsha has
to be
כסדרן. kasidran. So he says you need to check your קלף klaf
beforehand because you don't want there to be a problem ובעינן כתיבה
תמה, u-be'inan kethivah tama, we need a pure writing, which means מוקף
גויל mukaf gvil ולא קא, ve-la ka, and you wouldn't have it.
I'm sorry, so what you're saying is that if let's say you
check your תפילין tefillin and then one of them is,
one of the פרשיות parshiyos is פסול, pasul, you've got to take
out all the other four? All four פרשיות, parshiyos, unless you can
find, what they will do is they will date the פרשיות, parshiyos,
not written on but like with a little piece of paper attached
to it. And if you can find a פרשה, parsha, let's say
your פרשה parsha number three was פסול pasul of your four in
your של ראש, shel rosh, and three was פסול, pasul, if you
can find another number three that was written after number two and
before number four, you can replace it. But if you can't find
one that was, if your תפילין tefillin were written in 1972, okay,
you have to find a פרשה parsha that was written in June
1972 after number two and before number four. So it's going to
be a little bit difficult. So most of the time, if you
find one פסול pasul in your תפילין, tefillin, you have to do
it all over again because you need כסדרן kasidran also in terms
of the order of the
פרשיות. parshiyos. Therefore saying, check your קלף klaf beforehand so it shouldn't
turn out that there was a little hole near a letter and
the whole, why is that so important? As opposed to it just
being chronologically כסדרן? kasidran?
What do you mean? Meaning like if it's still כסדרן kasidran if
I have it in the correct order.
Oh, you're sorry, you mean that why is the order important, order
of writing important rather than the order of placement? Right. Okay, that's
one of the הלכות halachos of כסדרן, kasidran, it has to be
written כסדרן, kasidran, right. Okay, so now how would you feel if
somebody wrote it backwards, started the last פסוק pasuk and wrote reverse?
Would you say it's okay as long as the end product is
okay or could you understand that that's a problem? So it's a
similar type of an issue. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay, so דדילמא אית ביה ריעותא, de-dilma is bei re'usa, maybe
there will be a problem ובעינן כתיבה תמה, u-be'inan kethivah tama, you
need a perfect writing, meaning it's מוקף גויל mukaf gvil ולא קא
ve-la ka and you won't have it. רב דימי מנהרדעא Rav Dimi
mi-Narda אמר amar לא צריך, lo tzarich, you don't need to check
it ahead of time, קולמוסא בדיק ליה, kulmosa badik leh,
your quill will check it for you. As you're writing, you know,
if your quill encounters a bump, you'll feel it, and therefore that
will tell you whether there's a hole or not and you don't
need to do a pre-check.
All right, אמר רב יצחק amar Rav Yitzchak רצועות שחורות הלכה למשה
מסיני, retzu'os shechoros halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai, black רצועות retzu'os are הלכה למשה
מסיני. halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. Or one side you mean? We're going to
talk about that. מיתיבי, mitivei, I'll ask you on this, we have
a ברייתא. Braisah. תפילין אין קושרים אותו אלא במינו, tefillin ein koshsin
oso ella be-mino, you can only do the קשירה keshira of the
תפילין tefillin with their men, meaning with straps have to be leather,
okay, they can't be something else, it has to be leather straps.
But in terms of color, בין ירוקות בין שחורות בין לבנות, bein
yerokos bein shechoros bein levanos, whether you want them to be green
or black or white, געזונטערהייט gezunteheit for the color, but it has
to be leather. So however, says the ברייתא, Braisah, אדומות לא יעשה,
adumos lo ya'aseh, don't make red straps. Why not?
מפני גנאי ודבר אחר, mipnei gnai ve-davar acher, because it's improper and
some other thing we don't want to talk about. So what's the
גנאי gnai that it sort of, you know, makes you look bad?
So רש"י Rashi says, well, because people will think if it's red
what happened was that you had a lot of scabs and the
תפילין tefillin rubbed against the scabs and it's bloody, so people, you
know, it looks יאכ yech and people will think and makes you
look יאכ yech that you're, you know, that you got your תפילין
tefillin all bloody with your
scabs with your blood. What's a דבר אחר? davar acher? So רש"י
Rashi says, I don't know, you know, this is pretty far-fetched, רש"י
Rashi says that it means people will think that maybe you were
wearing תפילין tefillin while having sex with your wife who's a נדה
Niddah and that's how they got bloody. Now what you're doing wearing
תפילין tefillin while you're having sex who— your wife is a נדה,
Niddah, and how exactly the blood managed to get on the straps?
Okay, we're not, but anyway, that's the דבר אחר. Davar acher.
These are Frenchmen though.
Maybe. Anyway, אמר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda, so that's anyway that's
that's why it's not that I seen but I am sure somebody
must. אמר רבי יהודה: Amar Rabbi Yehuda: מעשה בתלמידו, Maaseh b'talmido, so
that's it's supposed to be leather, but it can be any color.
So אמר רבי יהודה,
Amar
Rabbi Yehuda, so there's a question we have to answer basically. Yeah,
we're not done, but we're not done quoting the ברייתא. Baraisa. מעשה
בתלמידו של רבי עקיבא, Maaseh b'talmido shel Rabbi Akiva, there was a
story with the student of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva שהיה קושר תפיליו
בלשון של תכלת. she'haya kosher tefillav b'lashon shel techeiles.
He would not use leather straps; he would use nice blue strings
to tie his תפילין. tefillin. Okay, so so so shocking. We assumed
that the straps are so central to the definition of תפילין, tefillin,
but if you think about it, you know, while the תורה Torah
doesn't actually describe too much of it either, it doesn't describe the
box, it doesn't describe the רצועות, retzuos, but anyway, to us in
our mind, you know, they're so central, and here we're saying, oh
yeah, you know, make sure it's leather. Doesn't matter color, make sure
it's leather. Oh yeah, and תלמידו של רבי עקיבא, talmido shel Rabbi
Akiva, he didn't even use leather. They used like a blue string.
So the גמרא's Gemara going to be a be a bit find
this objectionable, but nevertheless it's a fascinating story.
ולא אמר לו דבר, v'lo amar lo davar, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva didn't respond.
So the גמרא Gemara says: אפשר אותו צדיק ראה תלמידו ולא מיחה
בו? efshar oso tzaddik ra'ah talmido v'lo micha bo? So presumably the
ברייתא Baraisa says, so it's a little unclear if this is רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda himself talking or some anonymous voice responding to רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. It sounds like it might be רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda himself talking, as we'll see how the story ends. So, אפשר
אותו צדיק ראה תלמידו ולא מיחה בו? efshar oso tzaddik ra'ah talmido
v'lo micha bo? So is it possible that that צדיק tzaddik saw
his student doing something which is such a violation and he didn't
say anything, he didn't sort of protest? So אמר לו, amar lo,
so he said back to him, so again it sounds, you know,
אמר, amar, who's saying back to whom? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda saying
back to some anonymous voice. הן, hein, you know what, you're right.
לא ראהו, lo ra'ahu, he didn't see his student wearing this. ואם
ראהו, v'im ra'ahu, had he seen it, לא היה מניחו, lo haya
manicho, he would not have allowed him to wear it. So it's
like I'm telling you a story but you say that's impossible. Ah,
you're right, it's impossible, but it happened.
What?
No, but he didn't, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva didn't see it.
He didn't see it,
right. He didn't see that it actually happened.
נו באמת. Nu be'emes. Right. Similarly: מעשה בהורקנוס בנו של רבי אליעזר
בן הורקנוס, maaseh b'Hurkenos beno shel Rabbi Eliezer ben Hurkenos, so Hurkenos
the son of רבי אליעזר בן הורקנוס Rabbi Eliezer ben Hurkenos שהיה
קושר תפיליו בלשון של ארגמן, she'haya kosher tefillav b'lashon shel argaman, he
used a red straps, red strings, not the straps, it's not leather,
red strings to to put on his תפילין.
tefillin. ארגמן's Argaman a little bit different than אדום, adom, no?
What? Whatever, right, royal purple. Okay, ולא אמר לו דבר, v'lo amar
lo davar, and he didn't respond to him, his son was doing
this, he didn't respond. אפשר אותו צדיק ראה בנו ולא מיחה בו?
efshar oso tzaddik ra'ah beno v'lo micha bo? Is it possible such
a צדיק tzaddik should see his son doing something and not protest?
ולא מיחה בו? v'lo micha bo? אמרו לו, amru lo, so they
said, אמרו לו, amru lo, he said back to them. הן, hein,
you're right, לא ראהו, lo ra'ahu, so he didn't really see him.
ואם ראהו, v'im ra'ahu, had he seen him, לא היה מניחו. lo
haya manicho. Now, fascinating because we're not denying that his son actually
did it, or not denying that a student of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva actually did it. Presumably this was a real phenomenon going on
at the time. The only question was, was that did they turn
a blind eye to it, or do we assume that they didn't
really see it? Now, maybe they didn't really see it because this
ties into the earlier description of color. If red is, if blue
is okay and purple is okay, so maybe they saw blue and
purple but they didn't realize it was a string, they thought it
was a strap. So that could be how they misunderstood it. But
nevertheless, the idea that people were actually doing this shows number one,
that the idea of it being leather is was somewhat, you know,
not so consensus at a certain stage, that there really were these
divergent practices. The other interesting question to ask and I don't know
the answer is, is this also reflecting sectarian practices? You know, like
particularly you wonder like Karaites and others who have different ideas about
תפילין, tefillin, since so much of it is הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha
l'Moshe m'Sinai. I'm just speculating here, I have no idea. But you
know, maybe that the idea of אפשר אותו צדיק ראהו ולא מיחה
בו, efshar oso tzaddik ra'ahu v'lo micha bo, it sounds like it's
more than just a question of like some sense of halachic violation.
You know, there's some sense of like there's something bigger at stake
here, you know, he's so righteous and מיחה, micha, I don't know,
could be just halachic violation. But one does wonder if it's also
reflecting certain sectarian practices. And like, you know, and then you would
understand, well, you know, he didn't want to start picking a fight
with him, and how could he not pick a fight with him
if he's adopting, you know, certain practices that are, you know, that
are sectarian practices. So I think it's a very, what do you
call it, like suggestive or גמרא Gemara in terms of what were
these things going on. Regardless, as we know, of course, clearly we
פוסקן posken that it has to be leather. Now we get back
to so of course they would have been מוחה mocheh had they
seen. Now we get back to the question of color. But it
seems like other colors are okay. So how could you say it
has to be
שחור? shachor? Let's take a look. So it says like this, I
mean, yeah, front and back.
תניא מיהו, Tanya mihu, we taught nonetheless, בין ירוקות בין שחורות, bein
yerukos bein shechoros, whether green or black, ובין לבנות, u'vein levanos, or
white. So גמרא Gemara says: לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult.
כאן מבפנים כאן מבחוץ. kan mibifnim kan mibachutz.
Question is whether it's the outer part or the inner part. The
part that's exposed to the outside has to be black, the part
that's against your body it can be, does can be any color,
which again gets us back to the question about how could they
see red and blue, but maybe it flipped. Okay, anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says. אם מבפנים, im mibifnim,
if all we're discussing is the part of the leather facing your
body, מאי גנאי בדבר אחר איכא? mai gnai bdavar acher ika? Why
do we not like red because it looks disgusting, what disgusting is
it? Nobody sees it, it's against your body.
Somewhere at the bottom of the strap is gonna get bloody.
Well, that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. The
גמרא Gemara says זימנין דמתהפכן ליה, zimnin d'mithapchan leh,
sometimes it turns around, which, you know, anybody who's worn a של
ראש shel rosh knows that it happens, that, you know, your strap
can turn around. But even on the של יד shel yad maybe
it turns around. And as Mordechai says, if the גנאי gnai is
that it's rubbing against our skin, then that's particularly a problem on
the inner side, but we're concerned that sometimes it will be exposed.
So what the גמרא Gemara has here is a fascinating fact that
some of the תלמידים talmidim of the great תנאים Tannaim actually did
not wear leather straps, but regardless of that, we assume leather straps.
Black is הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai on the outside, the
inside not. Now, what about the actual בית bayit itself? You would
assume if the black is הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai on
the straps, of course it's הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai on
the בית. bayit. Take a look at this little תוספות Tosafot where
תוספות Tosafot
says רצועות שחורות retzuot shechorot near the
bottom. יש שעושים בתים של תפילין מקלף לבן ולא בעי שחרות אלא
רצועות.
yesh she'osim batim shel
tefillin miklaf lavan velo ba'ei shachrut ela retzuot. It's like what?! Some
people actually had white תפילין! tefillin! They didn't, they didn't color the
בית, bayit, they only colored the רצועה retzua because only the רצועות
retzuot are הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai. And even the way
it's brought in the שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch is, let me just
quote for you here,
I think he quotes it in different ways. One he says is
הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai. He says like
this: עור הרצועות or haretzuot he says have to be הלכה למשה
מסיני שיהיו הרצועות שחורות מבחוץ. Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai sheyihyu haretzuot shechorot mibachutz.
How about the actual בית bayit of the תפילין tefillin themselves? So
there he says, let me see if I quickly can find it.
But about while you're looking for that, סגי חריצין ממקום התפר sagi
charitzin mimakom hatefer which we mentioned before, דיעבד di'eved you don't need
to as long as it's a little bit separated on top. So
פשיטא? pishita? Yeah, no, is he also saying that like it really
could be combined in the bottom?
Here, wait a minute, in ל"ב ל"ז lamed bet lamed zayin the
שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch says עור הבתים צריך להיות מעור בהמה חיה
ועוף טהורים. or habatim tzarich lihyot me'or behema chaya ve'of tehorim.
Blah blah blah. And then he says... תפילין של ראש ושל יד
צריך שיהיו מרובעות.
tefillin shel rosh veshel yad
tzarich sheyihyu meruba'ot.
We're going to get up to that. And now where did he
get to the black? Excuse me. אה,
עור הבתים מצוה לעשותו
שחור. ah,
or habatim mitzvah la'asoto
shachor. It
doesn't say הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai. מצוה, mitzvah, it's better,
it's a good idea. So and the משנה ברורה Mishna Berura says
משמע דבדיעבד אינו מעכב. mashma d'bedi'eved eino me'akev.
And then he quotes the whole discussion. So for those of us
who wear תפילין tefillin on a regular basis and we assume absolutely
everything is הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai, to find out that
actually even according to the שלחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, not just, you
know, one day in a גמרא Gemara or something, you might מעיקר
הדין me'ikar hadin not even need black בתים batim is pretty shocking.
But wouldn't it still be a מצוה mitzvah then? Right.
That's for
whether or not you have a few pints right away. Ah, right.
You have to paint right away, right?
Or did something on the...
You can wait a little while. Thank you. Exactly. And we're going
to talk in a minute about how long the רצועות retzuot have
to be. The entire length of the רצועות retzuot is not halachically
defined as a רצועה retzua either. But if it's in the requisite
length of the רצועות, retzuot, then Mordechai is absolutely correct, because the
שחור shachor is הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai, you have to
fix it immediately, whereas by the בית bayit you have a little
bit more of a, a little more latitude.
I just wanted to understand Ravina. Ravina is saying actually really could
be physically together, could be one thing in, on the bottom as
long as they are separated on top?
Yeah, it sounds like him.
And it doesn't have to go all the way to the bottom.
That's definitely what he sounds like.
Yeah. It's no standard they used to get then. I mean, you
had to, people had to make the dye, it was not like...
Yeah, but the black of the תפילין, tefillin, although the ink, there's
all these הלכות, halachot, if you have תפילין tefillin and you see
that it's white, it's getting rubbed and it's not black or whatever,
and you know, you don't need to go to a תפילין tefillin
store and buy special dye, get out your black magic
marker and you're... We do buy these little paints or whatever in
the תפילין tefillin store, okay, but, and I have one in my
תפילין tefillin bag in case, you know, you ever find, whatever you
correct it, but yeah, you just get out your magic marker.
Rabbi Loves in the שיטה shita is he uses a Sharpie instead
of one of those designated just for the תפילין tefillin on it
you think?
That shouldn't be a problem about, about using it, it should be,
it should have הזמנה hazmana for the מצוה mitzvah basically?
All right, but the notes here on this things is stated that
Sharpie must be made from kosher ingredients all the way.
Ah, that's interesting point. I don't know if the, I don't know
if the magic marker... I imagine it's all chemicals. Probably all chemicals.
Okay, let's keep on going. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, תפילין מרובעות... tefillin
meruba'ot...
Everything okay there, Joe? Yeah. Okay. תפילין מרובעות, tefillin meruba'ot, the fact
they have to be square is הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha lemoshe misinai.
אמר רב פפא בתפרן, Amar Rav Papa bitfuran,
I mean
aside from the מעברתא, ma'abarta,
because it's not really square.
Right. You're saying the bottom...
we're not talking about the בית. bayit. We haven't gotten to the
תיתורא titora or the מעברתא. ma'abarta. Okay, we're talking about the cube,
what we call the cube. Okay, has to be square. אמר רב
פפא בתפרן ובאלכסונן, Amar Rav Papa bitfuran u'be'alchsonan, in their sewing
and in their diagonal. What does that mean? So presumably they mean
different things. The sewing means when you sew it, like you know,
we see that I showed you, it's sort of sewn, get it
right, this could even be sewn onto the actual תיתורא titora in
darkish brown leather, but nevertheless you use these stitches to seal it.
That those stitchings don't stretch it so that it no longer is
the square. So you have to be careful that the stitching doesn't
stretch it. And the other point is אלכסונן, alchsonan, the way you
measure the diagonal is the way you measure the squareness is that
the diagonal is the right amount. Meaning it's a little funny. What
do you mean, the way you measure the squareness? You measure this
side, you measure that side, and then of course you've got it
squared. If you, you see, you have to, well you have to
know that it's a right angle. Okay, but doing a diagonal doesn't
prove it's a right angle. So what does it mean that's a
diagonal? Now the diagonal is, you know the גמרא Gemara says in
a number of places that a diagonal of a one by one
triangle is one point four, which is its rounding estimate of the
square root of two. This is one point four one four etcetera.
It's much better than its approximation of pi. Yeah. Okay. So anyway,
so some would say that the reason it says אלכסונן alchsonan is
actually giving you a margin of error. It's actually saying as long
as the diagonal, which is maybe a little bit anachronistic because maybe
the גמרא Gemara wasn't aware of its margin of error, but it's
saying as long as the diagonal is one point four, it doesn't
have to be a perfect square. The way you determine is it
square enough? This side is one point zero zero one centimeters and
this side is one point zero zero zero zero three
centimeters. Oh, it's not a square. No, the way you determine is
it square enough is if the diagonal is one point four,
you know, of a squared plus b squared, whatever, then that would
be considered to be square enough. And that becomes a very important
question which is the halachic degree of precision and tolerance. So you
know, לא ניתנה תורה למלאכי השרת, lo nitna torah lemalachei hasharet, and
how square is square? So for some, the idea here, this becomes
an important model for that idea that you have a certain range
of tolerance here in what's defined as squareness. All right, so that's
the אלכסונן alchsonan and the diagonal.
So now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
Where were we?
Okay. לימא מסייע ליה, Leima mesayye lei, let me bring a proof
to you. העושה תפילתו עגולה סכנה ואין בה מצוה. Ha'oseh tefillato agula
sakana ve'ein bah mitzvah.
If you make your תפילין tefillin circular, or I would say spherical,
it's a סכנה sakana and there's no מצוה. mitzvah. No מצוה mitzvah
because it's not square. Why is it a סכנה? sakana? Because if
you have a sphere, a sphere you know really, if you think
about the way a ball rests on a table, it rests on
a point. So if you've got a sphere on your head, it's
resting on a point. And therefore if you walk into a door,
okay, how many people have walked into a door wearing תפילין? tefillin?
But I as a guy, got my head banged a few times
turning a corner and you know the wall hits your תפילין. tefillin.
Anyway, if you did that with a spherical של ראש, shel rosh,
it would push into your head and it would be a סכנה.
sakana. If it's flat, then it's you know, then it's distributed, the
pressure. So therefore it's a סכנה ואין בה מצוה. sakana ve'ein bah
mitzvah. So what do you see? You see that it has to
be square. Now the difference between not being spherical and requiring squareness
is a big difference, but anyway, which is what the גמרא Gemara
is going to say.
Yeah, your head is kind of spherical, so it's kind of rests,
it doesn't rest flat anyway. This.
Yeah, but it also doesn't create a point to push into your
head.
If your head, your head might push into your תפילין, tefillin, but
the תפילין tefillin isn't pushing into your head.
If you have a flat object on a sphere, it's
also resting on one point. I understand, but you can't push, if
the problem is you don't want to pierce into the sphere, right?
I don't care if my head pierces into the תפילין, tefillin, I
don't want the תפילין tefillin piercing into my head. So the problem
is that the תפילין tefillin can't be circular. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
So you see there that it has to be square. אמר רב
פפא מתניתין דעבידא כאיגוז. Amar Rav Papa matnitin de'avida ke'egoz.
No,
that doesn't prove that anything
that's not square is not good. Maybe that it can't be nut-shaped,
you know, which is almost like ellipsoid. That really comes to a
point and that'll really get into your skull. But if it's maybe
other types of things that are not squares, it's not a big
deal. So you can't prove it from that. And again, things that
we take for granted are so much absolute הלכה למשה מסיני halacha
lemoshe misinai
unquestionable, here's the גמרא Gemara is like, oh is that really true?
It needs to be a square? Let's try to prove it. Maybe
yes, maybe no, and so on. Okay. So let's try to do
that.
The other thing that's not clear here is the difference between square
and a cube, right? We have our תפילין tefillin that not only
is it square here at the bottom, right, but it also is
a cube, that the height is the same as the other
thing.
They said that it's מרבעת, Merubas, הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha L'Moshe Mi'Sinai.
That's an excellent point. You're right.
That's what you normally do, you know?
Unless somehow the רב פפא's Rav Papa point of the תפרא Tafra
meant because part of what תפרא Tafra can mean here if you
remember קטר Kessar was the way the גמרא Gemara was talking about
the point of connection with the תיתורא. Titora. So maybe the גמרא
Gemara understood, I was explaining רש״י. Rashi. רש״י Rashi said תפרא Tafra
means you shouldn't stretch the תפילין Tefillin away from its square shape,
but תפרא Tafra could also mean that it even has to be
square at the bottom. It's not enough that it's square as you
go up to height, but even at the תפרא, Tafra, even where
it connects. And then it's the question about how it rests on
your head. Okay, so maybe it's a good point, but maybe that's
exactly questioning רב פפא's Rav Papa interpretation of square. Does it have
to be square all the way to the bottom? Okay, so let's
take a look. אמר רב
הונא. Amar Rav Huna. רב הונא Rav Huna says, תפילין כל זמן
שפני טבלא קיימת כשרה. Tefillin kol zman she'pnei tavla kayemes kesheira. תפילין
Tefillin as long as the face of the the outer face is
appears, it's כשר, Kasher, meaning what happens if the inner compartments of
the של ראש Shel Rosh break? Right? Do these inner compartments, let's
say holes form inside, but the outer shape is the same? Okay,
is that okay or not? He says as long as the outer
shape remains correct, even if the inner walls break, it's okay.
אמר רב חסדא. Amar Rav Chisda. No, only if up to two
inner compartments is כשר. Kasher. שלוש, Shalosh, if all three inner walls,
there are four compartments, three walls, if all three inner walls break,
then it's not good. פסולה, Pesula, because that makes sense. If all
three inner walls break, then you don't have compartments. You basically just
have one בית. Bayis. The whole idea of compartments is that you
have walls inside. So let's just finish this. אמר רב פפא הא
דאמרת שתים כשירות. Amar Rav Papa ha d'amarta shtayim ksheiros. Two compartments
when they break it's כשר. Kasher. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, you mean.
אמר רבא Amar Rava that two compartments when they break it's כשר.
Kasher. לא אמרן אלא זה שלא כנגד זה. Lo amran ela zeh
shelo keneged zeh. It's only if the breaks, so if you see
these are your four בתים Batim and your three walls right here,
well actually no, one, two, three, four. Here, your four בתים Batim
and your, well these are your outer walls, your three inner walls.
So he would say if it's זו כשרא כנגד זו, zu ksheira
keneged zu, which means let's say you've got a break in this
wall and you've got a break in this wall. Okay, so although
you have a break in this wall and this wall, right, you
still have separate compartments because, you know, this wall is still whole.
So this wall at least divides, you know, creates some division. That's
okay.
It's not broken all the way through both sides of the...
Exactly. אבל זה כנגד זה פסולה. Aval zeh keneged zeh pesula.
If however it is a hole here and a hole here, so
you've totally lost any wall to this compartment. This wall has a
hole and this wall has a hole. Even if it's a little
hole each wall, it's okay? Right. So רש״י Rashi also says another
read of רש״י Rashi is זה כנגד זה zeh keneged zeh means
where in the wall is the hole? If I have a hole
down here and a hole up here, maybe it's not a problem
because the holes aren't facing one another. That's an even more מיקל
Meikel read. Okay, but to some degree if the holes are such
that it destroys that sense of a compartment.
Does it have to be a big enough hole?
I mean if it's like a needle hole, then probably not. Right,
that's also a question about how big of a hole. Correct. Okay,
and now the גמרא Gemara says,
let's really just wrap this up. וזה כנגד זה נמי לא אמרן.
Ve'zeh keneged zeh nami lo amran. When is it a problem? אלא
בחדתא, Ela be'chadta, if it's new תפילין, Tefillin, because the assumption is
a little ironically that if it's new then, you know, it's like
when you get your car right out of the, you know, shop,
not the shop, right out of the the lot. The tiniest little
scratch you notice, right? After you've owned it for a year, you
can like get a big scrape or eh, whatever, it just sort
of, I have enough of those as it is. So if it's
new, a little problem somehow stands out. Although ironically it's not visible.
It's all interior. But if it's new and it's whatever. So רש״י
Rashi says also that would indicate poor quality leather. If it's new
and it's already getting holes, then it's poor quality leather and that
invalidates everything. What?
Like you should have bought a lemon. Like when you drive off
the lot and you get like a little ping down, or it
was the brand new car, it's a bad sign versus a 20-year-old
car.
I see. Okay, anyway, so if it's new, it's a problem.
אבל בעתיקתא, Aval be'atika, if it's old, לית לן בה, leis lan
bah, we don't care.
אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, Amar lei Abaye l'Rav Yosef, היכי דמי
חדתא והיכי דמי עתיקתא? Heichi dami chadta ve'heichi dami atika? What's new,
what's old? אמר ליה כל היכא דכי מטו ליה בשיחא והדר חלים
עתיקתא. Amar lei kol heicha de'ki matu lei be'shicha ve'hadar chalim atika.
If you would stretch it, stretch the leather and it would recover,
like it would pull itself back, then it's old actually. ואידך חדתא.
Ve'idach chadta. It's new
because if it's brand new leather and you stretch it, you're going
to affect the shape. But if it's old worn leather, it's already
stretched. So if you stretch it out, it's not going to really,
it's not going to affect the shape so much. Okay. ואיכא דאמרי,
Ve'ika d'amri, or if you want,
כל היכא דכי מטו ליה במתנא אתיא בתרה
חדתא.
Kol heicha de'ki matu lei be'masna
asya basra chadta. And so רש״י Rashi says a couple reads of
רש״י, Rashi, but he basically says anytime if you stretch it, it
stretches with you, meaning if you pull it, it actually stretches, so
now it's a question of... recovering, but actually the pull affects the
shape, then it's new. ואידך ve'idach if your pulling it doesn't affect
the shape, עתיקא atika then it is old. Okay, so we will
end with this.